<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter>

  <title>Activiti Probe</title>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>  
    <para>
      Activiti Probe is a web application that provides administration and monitoring capabilities to keep an Activiti Engine instance up and running.  This is application is aimed at system administrators and operators whom are responsible for keeping systems and infrastructure up and running.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Process Engine Status</title>
    <para>
      The start page provides an overview of the status of an Activiti Engine instance, including the Activiti version you are using.
    </para>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.probe.status.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Job Management</title>
    <para>
  The jobs management page allows you to perform a number of job related tasks, including:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            View List of Jobs &amp; Job details
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Confirm Job Status
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Retry failed jobs
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Immediately send pending jobs for execution
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            View exception messages for failed jobs  
          </para>
        </listitem>    
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      When a job is executed, it is sent to an execution queue and run asynchronously, which means that the results of executing a job may not be visible in the data table immediately. Using the checkboxes on the right-hand end of each row, you are able to send multiple jobs for execution in the same request.
    </para>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.probe.jobs.selected.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    <para>
      If a job has failed there will be the option to view the exception, or error message from the job - this appears in a popup box on the same page.
    </para>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.probe.jobs.exception.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
  </section>
  
  <section id="probeDeployments">
    <title>Deployments</title>
    <para>
      On the deployments management page you can see each deployment that has been made into the Activiti Engine and when it was made.
    </para>
    <para>
      The management options for each deployment are to delete it ("Delete"), or to delete the deployment and all associated files, like processes and jobs ("Delete Cascade"). It is also possible to delete multiple deployments simultaneously by selecting more than one row in the data table. 
    </para>
    <para>
      The data table can be sorted by Id, Name or Deployment Time.
    </para>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.probe.deployments.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    
    <para>
      You can also upload new deployments from your browser using probe. When clicking the upload-button you can select a file to upload, this must be either a <emphasis role="bold">.bpmn20.xml, .zip or .bar</emphasis> file. 
      Once the deployment is performed successfully, the deployment appears in the list and the process(es) are ready to be used.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Database</title>
    <para>
      The database view gives administration users a view on the raw data in the data base. To ensure the consistency of the data, it is read only and cannot be modified from this view - to update any of the records one of supplied public API methods should be used. The database view shows the following tables:
    </para>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.probe.database.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
  </section>
  
</chapter>

