<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter>
  <title>Getting Started</title>
  
  <section id="demo.setup.one.minute.version">
    <title>One minute version</title>
    <para>
      After downloading the Activiti distribution zip file from the Activiti website,
      follow these steps to get the demo setup running with default settings:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Unzip the Activiti distribution zip file.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open up a terminal window and navigate to the <literal>setup</literal>
          folder in the unzipped folder.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Type <emphasis role="bold">ant demo.start</emphasis> and hit enter.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When the script finishes, it starts up all the Activiti webapps in your
          browser. Login with kermit/kermit.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      That's it! If you want to know more, read the <link linkend="demo.setup">longer version</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="demo.setup">
    <title>Demo setup</title>
    <para>'Demo Setup' is an ant script located in directory <literal>setup</literal> that
    sets up an Activiti environment in no time.
    </para>
    <para>To run the script, you'll need a working 
    <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp">Java runtime</ulink> and
    <ulink url="http://ant.apache.org/bindownload.cgi">Ant</ulink> installation.
    Also make sure that the <emphasis>JAVA_HOME</emphasis> and <emphasis>ANT_HOME</emphasis> system
    variables are correctly set. The way to do this depends on your operating system, but the
    <ulink url="http://ant.apache.org/manual/install.html">manual of ant</ulink> gives a description
    on how to do this. The demo setup script is tested with Ant 1.7.1+.
    </para>
    <para>If you don't provide any parameters, the demo setup will boot using default settings.
    To configure the setup for your environment, update the property files <literal>build.properties</literal> 
    and <literal>build.{your-database}.properties</literal> .  Check those files for more information on 
    configurable properties and potential values. 
    </para>
    <para>The easiest way to get started is open a command prompt in de <literal>setup</literal> folder 
    and type:
    </para>
    <programlisting>ant demo.start</programlisting>
    <para>This ant target will start a tomcat and a H2 database if you didn't change the default seetings.
    The first time when the script is executed, it will also perform following installations:  
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>(*) Build the webapps.  All libraries are stored in <literal>${actviti.home}/setup/files/dependencies/libs</literal>
        The webapps without the libs are stored in <literal>${actviti.home}/setup/files/webapps</literal>. Building the webapps means that
        webapps are combined with the necessary libraries in <literal>${actviti.home}/setup/build/webapps</literal> 
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Install the H2 in ${activiti.home}/apps/h2.  This only happens if you're using h2 as your database.  
        H2 is the default database.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Start the H2 database.  Again, this is only done if using h2 as the database.  If you're using 
        a different database it is assumed that it is already up and running.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Create the Activiti tables in the database</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Insert the demo users and groups in the Activiti identity tables (see below)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Deploy the example processes to the Activiti Engine DB</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Download Tomcat if not available in the ${downloads.dir}</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Install Tomcat in ${activiti.home}/apps/apache-tomcat-${tomcat.version}</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Create an Activiti configuration jar</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Deploy the REST interface webapp into tomcat</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Download the Activiti Modeler webapp to ${activiti.home}/webapps.  The license for the Activiti Modeler 
      is <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIT_License">MIT</ulink>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>(*) Deploy the Probe, Explorer and Modeler webapps into tomcat.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Start tomcat</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>(*) only performed the first time when running <literal>ant demo.start</literal> </para>
    <para>After running this target H2 and Tomcat will be running in the background.  To stop those 
    processes run <literal>ant demo.stop</literal>.</para>
    <para>The other targets in that build script can also be called individually and they will take the 
    configurable properties into account. Run <literal>ant -p</literal> for more details.
    </para>
    <para>These are the demo users:</para>
    <table>
      <title>The demo users</title>
      <tgroup cols='3'>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>UserId</entry>
            <entry>Password</entry>
            <entry>Security roles</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>kermit</entry>
            <entry>kermit</entry>
            <entry>admin</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>gonzo</entry>
            <entry>gonzo</entry>
            <entry>manager</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>fozzie</entry>
            <entry>fozzie</entry>
            <entry>user</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    
    <para>Now you can access following web applications:</para>
    <table>
      <title>The webapp tools</title>
      <tgroup cols='4'>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Webapp Name</entry>
            <entry>URL</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Activiti Probe</entry>
            <entry><ulink url="http://localhost:8080/activiti-probe">http://localhost:8080/activiti-probe</ulink> </entry>
            <entry>The admin management console.  Use this tool to see if the configured process engine is 
            correctly initialized, DB tables contents.
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Activiti Explorer</entry>
            <entry><ulink url="http://localhost:8080/activiti-explorer">http://localhost:8080/activiti-explorer</ulink> </entry>
            <entry>The process engine user console.  Use this tool to view your personal and candidate task lists and to 
            complete tasks.
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Activiti Cycle</entry>
            <entry><ulink url="http://localhost:8080/activiti-cycle">http://localhost:8080/activiti-cycle</ulink> </entry>
            <entry>The Activiti collabotation tool. Use this to browse repositories and execute transformations between model formats.
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Activiti Modeler powered by Signavio</entry>
            <entry><ulink url="http://localhost:8080/activiti-modeler">http://localhost:8080/activiti-modeler</ulink></entry>
            <entry>The web based process designer tool.  Use this tool to graphically author BPMN 2.0 compliant process definitions 
            files.</entry>
          </row>
           <row>
            <entry>Activiti KickStart</entry>
            <entry><ulink url="http://localhost:8080/activiti-kickstart">http://localhost:8080/activiti-kickstart</ulink></entry>
            <entry>Allows to specify processes quickly and efficiently in an adhoc way.
            Simple processes, quick prototypes and adhoc workflow are created in no time using KickStart.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    
    <para>
      Note that the Activiti demo setup is a way of showing the capabilities and functionality of
      Activiti as easy and as fast as possible. This does however, <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> mean
      that it is the only way of using Activiti. As Activiti is 'just a jar', it can 
      be embedded in any Java environment: with swing or on a Tomcat, JBoss, WebSphere, etc.
      Or you could very well choose to run Activiti as a typical, standalone BPM server.
      If it is possible in Java, it is possible with Activiti!
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="examples">
    <title>Example projects in the workspace</title>
    <para>The distribution contains a workspace directory containing a couple of example java projects:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	      <para><emphasis role="bold">activiti-engine-examples</emphasis>: This set of 
	      examples show the most common usage of Activiti: BPMN process definitions 
	      and process executions are stored in a DB and the examples make use of 
	      the persistent API.</para>
	      <para>This project contains the eclipse project files, an ant build file 
	      and a maven pom file.  The ant build file is independent of the maven pom.  Both
	      are there to show how you can use ant and maven respectively for building and deploying processes
	      as part of your build.
	      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">activiti-spring-examples</emphasis>: These examples
      show how you can use the Activiti Engine in a Spring environment.    
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">activiti-groovy-examples</emphasis>: These examples
      show the library dependencies for groovy and an example process with groovy scripting.    
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">activiti-jpa-examples</emphasis>: These examples
      show library dependencies and how you can work with JPA in Activiti.    
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">activiti-cycle-examples</emphasis>: This is a 
      project containing an demo example project for Activiti Cycle 
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">activiti-modeler-examples</emphasis>: This is a 
      file based model repository to which the Activiti Modeler is configured in the 
      demo setup. 
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para><xref linkend="eclipsesetup" /> shows how you can set up your eclipse environment to 
    play with these example projects.
    </para>
    <para>As part of the <literal>demo.start</literal>, the examples will be inflated.  This 
    means that all the libs and configuration files will be put in place.  If you don't run the <literal>demo.start</literal> 
    and you want to inflate the examples with libs in the appropriate place,  
    run this command in the setup directory:
    </para>
    <programlisting>ant inflate.examples</programlisting>
    <para>Once you've done that the <literal>activiti-engine-examples</literal> and 
    <literal>activiti-spring-examples</literal> will contain <literal>libs-runtime</literal>
    and <literal>libs-test</literal> directories containing the runtime dependency jars and 
    test time dependency jars respectively.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="librarydependencies">
    <title>Library dependencies</title>
    <para>In order to prevent that the distribution file becomes too big by libraries that are included multiple times,
    all the libraries are grouped into a single directory somewhere in the <literal>setup/files</literal>. 
    </para>
    <para>The ant scripts in the <literal>setup/build.xml</literal> can inflate the examples (target <literal>inflate.examples</literal>) with 
    the libs and they will include the appropriate libs when building the webapps. 
    </para>
    <para>All the libs are located in <literal>setup/files/dependencies/libs</literal> 
    And the following files in <literal>setup/files/dependencies</literal> describe the library dependencies:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><literal>libs.engine.runtime.txt</literal>: The library runtime dependencies to run 
        the Activiti Engine.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><literal>libs.engine.runtime.test.txt</literal>: The libraries that need to be added 
        to the ones in <literal>libs.engine.runtime.txt</literal> to run the tests
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><literal>libs.engine.runtime.feature.groovy.txt</literal>: The libraries that need to be added 
        to the ones in <literal>libs.engine.runtime.txt</literal> to use the groovy scripting capabilities.  
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><literal>libs.engine.runtime.txt</literal>: The libraries that need to be added 
        to the ones in <literal>libs.engine.runtime.txt</literal> to use the JPA variable reference capabilities.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><literal>libs.spring.runtime.txt</literal>: The library runtime dependencies to run 
        the Activiti Engine in a Spring environment.  (This list includes the libs in <literal>libs.engine.runtime.txt</literal>)
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><literal>libs.spring.runtime.test.txt</literal>: The libraries that need to be added 
        to the ones in <literal>libs.spring.runtime.txt</literal> to run tests in a Spring environment 
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><literal>libs.cycle.runtime.test.txt</literal>, <literal>libs.webapp.rest.txt</literal>
        and <literal>libs.webapp.ui.txt</literal>: The full list of libraries dependencies for the respective components
        cycle, the rest webapp and the UI webapps like Activiti Explorer, Activiti Probe and Activiti Cycle  
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section id="eclipsesetup">
    <title>Eclipse setup</title>
    <para>To run and play with the examples in your eclipse, follow these simple instructions:
    </para>
    <para>File --> Import...</para>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/eclipsesetup.import.existing.projects.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    <para>Select <literal>General --> Existing Projects into Workspace</literal> and click <literal>Next</literal> </para>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/eclipsesetup.import.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    <para>Click 'Browse...', select the directory <literal>${activiti.home}/workspace</literal> and you'll see 
    the example projects being automatically selected.
    </para>
    <para>Then you can click <literal>Finish</literal> in the Import dialog and you're all set.</para>
    <para>For more convenience, open the ant view (Window --> Show View --> Ant) and drag the 
    file <literal>activiti-engine-examples/build.xml</literal> into the ant window.  
    Now you'll be able to activate the build targets by just double clicking on them.</para>
    <para>If you want BPMN 2.0 XML auto-completion and validation while typing, you can add the BPMN 2.0
      XML Schema to the XML catalog. Go to <literal>Preferences --> XML --> XML Catalog --> Add</literal>, 
      and select the XML Schema from the file system in the folder <literal>docs/xsd/BPMN20.xsd</literal>.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/eclipse.setup.xml.catalog.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="inspecting.database">
    <title>Inspecting the database</title>
    <para>
      To check out the database while trying out the demo setup, run the following Ant target 
      in the <emphasis>setup</emphasis> folder:
      <programlisting>ant h2.console.start</programlisting>
      This will boot the H2 web console. Note that the Ant target doesn't return, so a <emphasis>'CTRL + C'</emphasis>
      is required to shutdown the console.
      Fill in the following URL in the <emphasis>JDBC URL</emphasis> field
      and click connect:
      <programlisting>jdbc:h2:tcp://localhost/activiti</programlisting>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/h2.console.login.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      You are now able to browse the Activiti database schema and check the content of the tables.
    </para>
    <para>To change the database, see <xref linkend="changingTheDatabase" />
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="database.tables.explained">
    <title>Database table names</title>
    <para>
      The database names of Activiti all start with <emphasis role="bold">ACT_</emphasis>. The 
      second part is a two-character identification of use case of the table. This use case 
      will also roughly match the service API.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">ACT_RE_*</emphasis>: 'RE' stands for <literal>repository</literal>. 
            Tables with this prefix will contain 'static'' information such as process definitions and,
            process resources (images, rules, etc.).
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">ACT_RU_*</emphasis>: 'RE' stands for <literal>runtime</literal>.
            These are the runtime tables, that contain the runtime data of process instances,
            user tasks,variables, jobs, etc. Activiti only stores the runtime data during process instance
            execution, and removes the records when a process instance ends. This keeps 
            the runtime tables small and fast.
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">ACT_ID_*</emphasis>: 'ID' stands for <literal>identity</literal>.
            These tables contain identity information, suchas users, groups, etc.
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">ACT_HI_*</emphasis>: 'HI' stands for <literal>history</literal>.
            These are the tables that contain historic data, such as past process instances,
            variables, tasks, etc.
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">ACT_GE_*</emphasis>: <literal>general</literal> data, which is used
            in various use cases.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  
</chapter>
