<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chDeployment">
  <title>Deployment</title>

  <section>
    <title>Business archives</title>
    <para>To deploy processes, they have to be wrapped in a business archive.  A business archive is the unit 
    of deployment to an Activiti Engine.  Basically a business archive is equivalent to a zip file.  It can contain 
    BPMN 2.0 processes, task forms, rules and any other type of file.  In general, a business archive 
    contains a collection of named resources.  
    </para>
    <para>When a business archive is deployed, it is scanned for BPMN files with a <literal>.bpmn20.xml</literal> extension.
    Each of those will be parsed and potentially contains multiple process definitions.  
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that Java classes present in the business archive <emphasis role="bold">will not be added to the classpath.</emphasis> All custom classes used in process definitions in the business archive (for example Java service tasks or event listener implementations) should be present
      on the activiti-engine's classpath in order to run the processes. 
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Java classes</title>
    <para>All custom classes that are used in your process (eg. JavaDelegates used in servicetaks or event-listeners, TaskListeners, ...) should be present on the engine's classpath when an instance of the process is started.
    It's not nessecairy to have those classes on the classpath when deploying the process-definition into the engine.
    </para>
    <para>
    When you are using the demo setup and you want to add your custom classes, you should add a jar containing your classes to the activiti-rest webapp lib. Don't forget to include the dependencies of your custom classes (if any) as wel. 
    This is the same location where the activiti-engine jar is located. You can find this folder inside your distro at the folowing location: 
    </para>
    <para>
    <programlisting>${activiti distro}/apps/apache-tomcat-6.0.29/webapps/activiti-rest/lib/</programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Deploying with Activiti Probe</title>
    <para>In <link linkend="probeDeployments">page 'Deployments' in Activiti Probe</link>, you can upload a
    business archive to deploy it in the Activiti Engine.  
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Deploying programmatically</title>
    <para>Deploying a business archive from a zip file can be done like this: 
    </para>
    <programlisting>String barFileName = "path/to/process-one.bar";
ZipInputStream inputStream = new ZipInputStream(new FileInputStream(barFileName));
    
repositoryService.createDeployment()
    .name("process-one.bar")
    .addZipInputStream(inputStream)
    .deploy();
</programlisting>
    <para>It's also possible to build a deployment from individual resources. 
    See javadocs for more details.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Deploying with ant</title>
    <para>To deploy a business archive with ant, first the <literal>deploy-bar</literal> task 
    needs to be defined.  Make sure that the configuration jar is on the classpath, as well as the 
    Activiti jar and all its dependencies:</para>
    <programlisting>&lt;taskdef name=&quot;deploy-bar&quot; classname=&quot;org.activiti.engine.impl.ant.DeployBarTask&quot;&gt;
  &lt;classpath&gt;
    &lt;fileset dir=&quot;...&quot;&gt;
      &lt;include name=&quot;activiti-cfg.jar&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;include name=&quot;your-db-driver.jar&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/fileset&gt;
    &lt;fileset dir=&quot;${activiti.home}/lib&quot;&gt;
      &lt;include name=&quot;activiti-engine-${activiti.version}.jar&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;include name=&quot;ibatis-sqlmap-*.jar&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/fileset&gt;
  &lt;/classpath&gt;
&lt;/taskdef&gt;
&lt;deploy-bar file=&quot;.../yourprocess.bar&quot; /&gt;</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Deploying with Activiti Probe</title>
    <para>It's possible to deploy process definitions through probe, this is described in <link linkend="probeDeployments">Activiti Probe - Deployments</link>.</para>  
  </section>
  
  <section id="versioningOfProcessDefinitions">
    <title>Versioning of process definitions</title>
    <para>BPMN doesn't have a notion of versioning.  And that is good because the executable BPMN process 
    file will probably live in an SVN repository as part of your development project.  Versions of process definitions
    are created during deployment. During deployment, Activiti will assign a version to the <literal>ProcessDefinition</literal> 
    before it is stored in the Activiti DB.
    </para>
    <para>For each process definition in a business archive the following steps are performed to 
    initialize the properties <literal>key</literal>, <literal>version</literal>, <literal>name</literal> and <literal>id</literal>:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>The process definition <literal>id</literal> attribute in the XML file is used as the process definition <literal>key</literal> property</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The process definition <literal>name</literal> attribute in the XML file is used as the process definition <literal>name</literal> property.
        If the name attribute is not specified, then id attribute is used as the name.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The first time a process with a particular key is deployed, version 1 is assigned.  For all subsequent deployments of
      process definitions with the same key, the version will be set 1 higher then the max currently deployed version.  The key property
      is used to distinct process definitions.</para></listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The id property is set to {processDefinitionKey}:{processDefinitionVersion}:{generated-id},
          where <literal>generated-id</literal> is a unique number added to guarantee uniquencess
          of the process id for the process definition caches in a clustered environment.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>
      Take for example the following process
<programlisting>
&lt;definitions id=&quot;myDefinitions&quot; &gt;
  &lt;process id=&quot;myProcess&quot; name=&quot;My important process&quot; &gt;
    ...      
</programlisting>    
      When deploying this process definition, the process definition in the database will look as follows
      <table>
        <title></title>
        <tgroup cols='4'>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>id</entry>
              <entry>key</entry>
              <entry>name</entry>
              <entry>version</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>myProcess:1:676</entry>
              <entry>myProcess</entry>
              <entry>My important process</entry>
              <entry>1</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      Suppose we now deploy an updated version of the same process (eg. changing some user tasks),
      but the <literal>id</literal> of the process definition remains the same. The process
      definition table will now contain following entries:
       <table>
        <title></title>
        <tgroup cols='4'>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>id</entry>
              <entry>key</entry>
              <entry>name</entry>
              <entry>version</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>myProcess:1:676</entry>
              <entry>myProcess</entry>
              <entry>My important process</entry>
              <entry>1</entry>
            </row><row>
              <entry>myProcess:2:870</entry>
              <entry>myProcess</entry>
              <entry>My important process</entry>
              <entry>2</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table> 
      When the <literal>runtimeService.startProcessInstanceByKey("myProcess")</literal> is called,
      it will now use the process definition with version <literal>2</literal>, as this is the 
      latest version of the process definition.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="providingProcessDiagram">
    <title>Providing a process diagram</title>
    <para>
      A process diagram image can be added to a deployment. This image will be stored in 
      the Activiti repository and is accessible through the API. Tis image is also used
      to visualize the process in Activiti Explorer.
    </para>
    <para>
      Suppose we have a process on our classpath, <literal>org/activiti/expenseProcess.bpmn20.xml</literal> that has
      as process key 'expense'.
      Following naming conventions for the process diagram image apply (in this specific order):
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If in the deployment an image resource with as name the BPMN 2.0 xml file name
            concatenated with the process key and an image suffix exists, this image is used. In our example,
            this would be <literal>org/activiti/expenseProcess.expense.png</literal> (or .jpg/gif).
            In case you have multiple images defined in one BPMN 2.0 xml file, this approach 
            makes most sense. Each diagram image will then have the process key in its file name.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If no such image exists, am image resource in the deployment matching the name
            of the BPMN 2.0 xml file is searched. In our example this would be 
            <literal>org/activiti/expenseProcess.png</literal>. Note that this means that
            <emphasis role="bold">every process definition</emphasis> defined in the same 
            BPMN 2.0 file has the same process diagram image. In case there is only one 
            process definition in each BPMN 2.0 xml file, this is of course no problem.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </para>
     <para>
      Example when deploying programmatically:
      <programlisting>
repositoryService.createDeployment()
  .name("expense-process.bar")
  .addClasspathResource("org/activiti/expenseProcess.bpmn20.xml")
  .addClasspathResource("org/activiti/expenseProcess.png")
  .deploy();</programlisting>
       The image resource can then later be retrieved through the API:
       <programlisting>
  ProcessDefinition processDefinition = repositoryService.createProcessDefinitionQuery()
                                                         .processDefinitionKey("expense")
                                                         .singleResult();
  
  <emphasis role="bold">String diagramResourceName = processDefinition.getDiagramResourceName();</emphasis>
  InputStream imageStream = repositoryService.getResourceAsStream(processDefinition.getDeploymentId(), diagramResourceName);
       </programlisting>
     </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="generatingProcessDiagram">
    <title>Generating a process diagram</title>
    <para>
      In case no image is provided in the deployment, as described in the <link linkend="providingProcessDiagram">previous section</link>,
      the Activiti engine will generate a diagram image when the process definition
      contains the necessary 'diagram interchange' information. This is the case when using the
      Activiti Modeler (and in the near future when using the Activiti Eclipse Designer).
    </para>
    <para>
      The resource can be retrieved in exactly the same way as when <link linkend="providingProcessDiagram">
      an image is provided</link> in the deployment.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/deployment.image.generation.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
