<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="bpmn20">
	<title>BPMN 20 Introduction</title>

	<section id="whatIsBpmn">

		<title>What is BPMN?</title>

		<para>
		  See our <ulink url="http://activiti.org/faq.html#WhatIsBpmn20">FAQ entry on BPMN 2.0</ulink>.
		</para>

	</section>

	<section id="bpmnExamples">

		<title>Examples</title>

		<para>
		  Examples for the BPMN 2.0 constructs described in the following sections can be 
		  found in the <emphasis>workspace/activiti-x-examples</emphasis> folders of the Activiti distribution. 
	  </para>
	  
	  <para>	  
		  See the specific section on <link linkend="examples">examples</link> for more information.
		</para>

	</section>

	<section id="bpmnDefiningProcess">

		<title>Defining a process</title>

		<para>
      To create a new BPMN 2.0 process definition, it's best to have your Eclipse
      <link linkend="eclipsesetup">properly set up</link>.		  
		</para>
		
		<para>
		  Create a new XML file (<emphasis>rightclick on any project and select New->Other->XML-XML File</emphasis>) and give it a name.
		  Make sure that the file <emphasis role="bold">ends with .bpmn20.xml</emphasis>, since
		  otherwise the engine won't pick up this file for deployment.
		  <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/new.bpmn.procdef.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
		</para>
		
		<para>
		  The root element of the BPMN 2.0 schema is the <emphasis role="bold">definitions</emphasis> element.
		  Within this element, multiple process definitions can be defined (although we advise to have only one
		  process definition in each file, since this simplifies maintenance later in the development process).
		  An empty process definition looks as follows. Note that the minimal definitions element
		  only needs the <emphasis>xmlns</emphasis> and <emphasis>targetNamespace</emphasis> declaration.
		  The targetNamespace can be anything, and is useful for categorizing process definitions.
		  <programlisting>
&lt;definitions 
  xmlns=&quot;http://www.omg.org/spec/BPMN/20100524/MODEL&quot;
  xmlns:activiti=&quot;http://activiti.org/bpmn&quot;
  targetNamespace=&quot;Examples&quot;&gt;

  &lt;process id=&quot;myProcess&quot; name=&quot;My First Process&quot;&gt;
    ..
  &lt;/process&gt;

&lt;/definitions&gt;</programlisting>
		</para>
		
		<para>
		  Optionally you can also add the online schemalocation of the BPMN 2.0 XML schema,
		  as an alternative to the  <link linkend="eclipsesetup">XML catalog configuration in Eclipse</link>.
		  <programlisting>
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.omg.org/spec/BPMN/20100524/MODEL 
                    http://www.omg.org/spec/BPMN/2.0/20100501/BPMN20.xsd</programlisting>
		</para>
		
		<para>
		  The process element has two attributes:
		  <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>
		        <emphasis role="bold">id</emphasis>: this attribute is <emphasis role="bold">required</emphasis>
		        and maps to the <emphasis role="bold">key</emphasis> property of an Activiti <emphasis>
		        ProcessDefinition</emphasis> object.
		        This id can then be used to start a new process instance of the process definition, through the 
		        <emphasis>startProcessInstanceByKey</emphasis> method on the <literal>RuntimeService</literal>.
		        This method will always take the <emphasis role="bold">latest deployed version</emphasis>
		        of the process definition.
		        <programlisting>ProcessInstance processInstance = runtimeService.startProcessInstanceByKey("myProcess");</programlisting>
		        Important to note here is that this is not the same as calling the 
		        <emphasis>startProcessInstanceById</emphasis> method. This method expects the String id 
		        that was generated at deploy time by the Activiti engine, and can be retrieved by calling the
		        <emphasis>processDefinition.getId()</emphasis> method.
		        The format of the generated id is <emphasis role="bold">'key:version'</emphasis>, 
		        and the length is <emphasis role="bold">constrained to 64 characters</emphasis>.
		        If you get an <emphasis>ActivitiException</emphasis> stating that the generated id
		        is too long, limit the text in the <emphasis>key</emphasis> field of the process.
		      </para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis>: this attribute is <emphasis role="bold">optional</emphasis>
            and maps to the <emphasis>name</emphasis> property of a <emphasis>ProcessDefinition</emphasis>.
            The engine itself doesn't use this property, so it can for example be used for displaying a more
            human-friendly name in a user interface.
          </para>
        </listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		</para>

	</section>
	
	<section id="10minutetutorial">
	
    <title>Getting started: 10 minute tutorial</title>
    
    <para>
      In this section we will cover a (very simple) business process that we will use to introduce
      some basic Activiti concepts and the Activiti API. 
    </para>
    
    <section id="bpmn10MinuteTutorialPrerequisites">
    
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      
      <para>
        This tutorial assumes that you have the <link linkend="demo.setup.one.minute.version">Activiti demo setup running</link>.
        Optionally, you should also have an Eclipse installed and <link linkend="eclipsesetup">imported the Activiti examples</link>.
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="bpmn10MinuteTutorialGoal">
    
      <title>Goal</title>
      
      <para>
        The goal of this tutorial is to learn about Activiti and some basic BPMN 2.0 concepts.
        The end result will be a simple Java SE program that deploys a process definition,
        and interacts with this process through the Activiti engine API. We'll also touch
        some of the tooling around Activiti. Of course, what you'll learn in this tutorial can 
        also be used when building your own web applications around your business processes.
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="bpmnFirstExampleUseCase">
      
      <title>Use case</title>
      
      <para>
				The use case is straightforward: we have a company, let's call it BPMCorp.
				In BPMCorp, a financial report needs to be written every month for the
				company shareholders. This is the responsibility of the accountancy
				department. When the report is finished, one of the members of the
				upper management needs to approve the document before it is sent to all
				the shareholders.
      </para> 
      
      <para>
        All files and code snippets used through the next sections can be found
        in the <link linkend="examples">examples</link> shipped with the Activiti distribution.
        Look for the package <emphasis>org.activiti.examples.bpmn.usertask</emphasis>.
      </para>   
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="bpmnFirstExampleDiagram">
    
      <title>Process diagram</title>
    
      <para>
				The business process as described above, can be graphically visualized
				using the  
				<link linkend="activitiDesigner">Activiti Designer</link>. However, for this tutorial
				we'll type the XML ourselves, as this learns us the most at this point. 
				The graphical BPMN 2.0 notation of our process looks like this:
			  <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/financial.report.example.diagram.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
        What we see is a <link linkend="bpmnNoneStartEvent">None Start Event</link> (circle on the left),
        followed by two <link linkend="bpmnUserTask">User Tasks</link>:
        <emphasis>'Write monthly financial report'</emphasis> and 
        <emphasis>'Verify monthly financial report'</emphasis>, ending in
        a <link linkend="bpmnNoneEndEvent">none end event</link> (circle with thick border on the right).
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="bpmnFirstExampleXml">
    
      <title>XML representation</title>
      
      <para>
        The XML version of this business process (<emphasis>FinancialReportProcess.bpmn20.xml</emphasis>) looks as shown below.
        It's easy to recognize the main elements of our process (click on the links
        for going to the detailed section of that BPMN 2.0 construct):
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The <link linkend="bpmnNoneStartEvent">(none) start event</link>
              learns us what the <emphasis>entry point</emphasis> to the process is.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The <link linkend="bpmnUserTask">User Tasks</link> declarations are the representation
              of the human tasks of our process. Note that the first task is assigned
              to the <emphasis>accountancy</emphasis> group, while the second task is 
              assigned to the <emphasis>management</emphasis> group.
              See <link linkend="bpmnUserTaskAssignment">the section on user task assignment</link>
              for more information on how users and groups can be assigned
              to user tasks.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The process ends when the <link linkend="bpmnNoneEndEvent">none end event</link>
              is reached.
            </para> 
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The elements are connected with each other through <link linkend="bpmnSequenceFlow">sequence flows</link>.
              These sequence flow have a <emphasis>source</emphasis> and <emphasis>target</emphasis>,
              defining the <emphasis>direction</emphasis> of the sequence flow.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <programlisting>
&lt;definitions id=&quot;definitions&quot;
  targetNamespace=&quot;http://activiti.org/bpmn20&quot; 
  xmlns:activiti=&quot;http://activiti.org/bpmn&quot;
  xmlns=&quot;http://www.omg.org/spec/BPMN/20100524/MODEL&quot;&gt;
	
	&lt;process id=&quot;financialReport&quot; name=&quot;Monthly financial report reminder process&quot;&gt;
	  
	  &lt;startEvent id=&quot;theStart&quot; /&gt;
	    
	  &lt;sequenceFlow id='flow1' sourceRef='theStart' targetRef='writeReportTask' /&gt;
	    
	  &lt;userTask id=&quot;writeReportTask&quot; name=&quot;Write monthly financial report&quot; &gt;
	    &lt;documentation&gt;
	      Write monthly financial report for publication to shareholders.
	    &lt;/documentation&gt;
	    &lt;potentialOwner&gt;
	      &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
	        &lt;formalExpression&gt;accountancy&lt;/formalExpression&gt;
	      &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
	    &lt;/potentialOwner&gt;
	  &lt;/userTask&gt;
	    
	  &lt;sequenceFlow id='flow2' sourceRef='writeReportTask' targetRef='verifyReportTask' /&gt;
	      
	  &lt;userTask id=&quot;verifyReportTask&quot; name=&quot;Verify monthly financial report&quot; &gt;
	    &lt;documentation&gt;
	      Verify monthly financial report composed by the accountancy department.
	      This financial report is going to be sent to all the company shareholders.  
	    &lt;/documentation&gt;
	    &lt;potentialOwner&gt;
	      &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
	        &lt;formalExpression&gt;management&lt;/formalExpression&gt;
	      &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
	    &lt;/potentialOwner&gt;
	  &lt;/userTask&gt;
	    
	  &lt;sequenceFlow id='flow3' sourceRef='verifyReportTask' targetRef='theEnd' /&gt;
	      
	  &lt;endEvent id=&quot;theEnd&quot; /&gt;
	      
	&lt;/process&gt;
	
&lt;/definitions&gt;</programlisting>        
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="bpmnFirstExamplStartProcess">
    
      <title>Starting a process instance</title>
      
      <para>
        We now have created the <emphasis role="bold">process definition</emphasis> of our
        business process. From such a process
        definition, we can create <emphasis role="bold">process instances</emphasis>.
        In this case, one process instance would match with the creation and verification
        of the financial report every month. All the process instances share the same process definition.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        To be able to create process instances from a given process definition,
        we must first <emphasis role="bold">deploy</emphasis> this process definition.
        Deploying a process definition means two things:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The process definition will be stored in the persistent datastore that
              is configured for your Activiti engine. So by deploying our business process,
              we make sure that the engine will find the process definition after an engine reboot.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The BPMN 2.0 process file will be parsed to an in-memory object model
              that can be manipulated through the Activiti API.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        More information on deployment can be found <link linkend="chDeployment">in the dedicated section on deployment</link>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        As described in that section, deployment can happen in several
        ways. One way is through the API as follows. Note that all interaction with the Activiti
        engine happens through its <emphasis>services</emphasis>.
        <programlisting>Deployment deployment = repositoryService.createDeployment()
  .addClasspathResource("FinancialReportProcess.bpmn20.xml")
  .deploy();</programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Now we can start a new process instance using 
        the <emphasis>id</emphasis> we defined in the process definition (see process element in the XML file).
        Note that this <emphasis>id</emphasis> in Activiti terminology
        is called the <emphasis role="bold">key</emphasis>.
        <programlisting>ProcessInstance processInstance = runtimeService.startProcessInstanceByKey("financialReport");</programlisting>
        This will create a process instance that
        will go first through the start event. After the start event, it follows all the outgoing
        sequence flow (only one in this case) and the first task ('write monthly financial report')
        is reached. The Activiti engine will now store a task in the persistent database. 
        At this point, the user or group assignments attached to the task are resolved and also stored in the 
        database. It's important to note that the Activiti engine will continue process execution steps
        until it reaches a <emphasis>wait state</emphasis>, such as the user task. At such a wait state,
        the current state of the process instance is stored in the database. It remains in that
        state until a user decides to complete its task. At that point, the engine will continue 
        until it reaches a new wait state or the end of the process. When the engine reboots or crashes
        in the meantime, the state of the process is safe and well in the database.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        After the task is created, the <emphasis>startProcessInstanceByKey</emphasis> method will return
        since the user task activity is a <emphasis>wait state</emphasis>, In this case, the task is assigned to a group, which means that the every
        member of the group is a <emphasis role="bold">candidate</emphasis> to perform the task.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        We can now throw this all together and create a simple Java program. Create a new 
        Eclipse project and add the Activiti jars and dependencies to its classpath 
        (these can be found <emphasis>setup/files/dependencies/libs</emphasis>).
        Before we can call the Activiti services, we must first construct a <literal>ProcessEngine</literal>
        that gives us access to the services. Here we use the <emphasis>'standalone'</emphasis> configuration,
        that constructs a ProcessEngine that uses the database also used in the demo setup.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        You can download the process definition XML <ulink url="images/FinancialReportProcess.bpmn20.xml">here</ulink>. This file
        contains the XML as shown above, but contains also the necessary BPMN 
        <link linkend="generatingProcessDiagram">diagram interchange information</link> to
        visualize the process in the Activiti tools.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <programlisting>
public static void main(String[] args) {
    
  // Create Activiti process engine
  ProcessEngine processEngine = ProcessEngineConfiguration
    .createStandaloneProcessEngineConfiguration()
    .buildProcessEngine();
  
  // Get Activiti services
  RepositoryService repositoryService = processEngine.getRepositoryService();
  RuntimeService runtimeService = processEngine.getRuntimeService();
  
  // Deploy the process definition
  repositoryService.createDeployment()
    .addClasspathResource(&quot;FinancialReportProcess.bpmn20.xml&quot;)
    .deploy();
    
  // Start a process instance
  runtimeService.startProcessInstanceByKey(&quot;financialReport&quot;);
}</programlisting>
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="bpmnFirstExampleCandidateList">
    
      <title>Task lists</title>  
      
      <para>
        We can now retrieve this task through the <emphasis>taskService</emphasis> by adding following logic:
        <programlisting>List&lt;Task&gt; tasks = taskService.createTaskQuery().taskCandidateUser(&quot;kermit&quot;).list();</programlisting>
        Note that the user we pass to this operation needs to be a member of 
        the <emphasis>accountancy</emphasis> group, since that was declared in the process definition:
        <programlisting>
&lt;potentialOwner&gt;
  &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
    &lt;formalExpression&gt;<emphasis role="bold">accountancy</emphasis>&lt;/formalExpression&gt;
  &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
&lt;/potentialOwner&gt;</programlisting>
     
        We could also use the task query API to get the same results using the name of the group.
        We can now add following logic to our code:
         <programlisting>
TaskService taskService = processEngine.getTaskService();
List&lt;Task&gt; tasks = taskService.createTaskQuery().taskCandidateGroup(&quot;accountancy&quot;).list();</programlisting>
</para>
      
      <para>
        Since we've configured our ProcessEngine to use the same database as the demo setup is using (run the <link linkend="demo.setup">demo setup</link> if you haven't done it yet'),
        we can now log into <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/activiti-explorer/">Activiti Explorer</ulink> 
        (login with fozzie/fozzie), and we fill find that we can start our business process after
        selecting the <emphasis>Processes</emphasis> page and
        and clicking on the <emphasis>'Start Process'</emphasis> link in the <emphasis>'Actions'</emphasis> column corresponding to the <emphasis>'Monthly financial report'</emphasis> process.
        
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn.financial.report.example.start.process.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
        
        As explained, the process will execute up to the first user task. Since we're logged in
        as kermit, we can see that there is a new candidate task available for him after we've started
        a process instance. Select the <emphasis>Tasks</emphasis> page to view this new task. 
        Note that even if the process was started by someone else, the task would still
        be visible as a candidate task to everyone in the accountancy group.
        
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn.financial.report.example.task.assigned.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
        
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="bpmnFirstExampleClaimTask">
    
      <title>Claiming the task</title>
      
      <para>
        An accountant now needs to <emphasis role="bold">claim the task</emphasis>. By claiming the
        task, the specific user will become the <emphasis role="bold">assignee</emphasis> of the task
        and the task will disappear from every task list of the other members of the accountancy group.
        Claiming a task is programmatically done as follows:
        <programlisting>taskService.claim(task.getId(), &quot;fozzie&quot;);</programlisting>
        The task is now in the <emphasis role="bold">personal task list of the one
        that claimed the task</emphasis>.
        <programlisting>List&lt;Task&gt; tasks = taskService.createTaskQuery().taskAssignee(&quot;fozzie&quot;).list();</programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        In the Activiti Explorer UI, clicking the <emphasis>claim</emphasis> button will
        call the same operation. The task will now move to the personal task list of the logged
        on user. You also see that the assignee of the task changed to the current logged in user.
        
       <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn.financial.report.example.claim.task.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
    </section>
      
    <section id="bpmnFirstExampleCompleteTask">
    
      <title>Completing the task</title>
      
      <para>
        The accountant can now start working on the financial report. Once the report is finished,
        he can <emphasis role="bold">complete the task</emphasis>, which means that all
        work for that task is done.
        <programlisting>taskService.complete(task.getId());</programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        For the Activiti engine, this is an external signal that the process instance execution
        must be continued. The task itself is removed from the runtime data.
        The single outgoing transition out of the task is followed, bringing
        the execution in the second task (<emphasis>'verification of the report'</emphasis>). 
        The same mechanism as described for the first task will now
        happen, with the small difference that the task will be assigned to the 
        <emphasis>management</emphasis> group.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        In the demo setup, completing the task is done by clicking the <emphasis>complete</emphasis>
        button in the task list. Since Fozzie isn't an accountant, we need to log out of
        the Activiti Explorer and login in as <emphasis>kermit</emphasis> (which is a manager).
        The second task is now visible in the unassigned task lists.
      </para>
      
    </section>
      
    <section id="bpmnFirstExampleEndingProcess">

      <title>Ending the process</title>
        
      <para>
        The verification task can be retrieved and claimed in exactly the same way as before.
        Completing this second task, will bring process execution at the end event, which finishes
        the process instance. The process instance and all related runtime execution data
        is removed from the datastore.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        When you log into Activiti Explorer you can verify this, since no records will be 
        found in the table where the process executions are stored.
        
         <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn.financial.report.example.process.ended.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject> 
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Programmatically, you can also verify that the process is ended using the <literal>historyService</literal>
        <programlisting>
HistoryService historyService = processEngine.getHistoryService();
HistoricProcessInstance historicProcessInstance = 
historyService.createHistoricProcessInstanceQuery().processInstanceId(procId).singleResult();
System.out.println(&quot;Process instance end time: &quot; + historicProcessInstance.getEndTime());</programlisting>
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="bpmnFirstExampleCode">
    
      <title>Code overview</title>
      
      <para>
        Taking all the snippets from previous sections, and you should have something like this
        (this code takes in account that you probably will have started a few process instances
        through the Activiti Explorer UI. As such, it always retrieves a list of tasks instead
        of one task, so it works always):
        <programlisting>
public class TenMinuteTutorial {
  
  public static void main(String[] args) {
    
    // Create Activiti process engine
    ProcessEngine processEngine = ProcessEngineConfiguration
      .createStandaloneProcessEngineConfiguration()
      .buildProcessEngine();
    
    // Get Activiti services
    RepositoryService repositoryService = processEngine.getRepositoryService();
    RuntimeService runtimeService = processEngine.getRuntimeService();
    
    // Deploy the process definition
    repositoryService.createDeployment()
      .addClasspathResource(&quot;FinancialReportProcess.bpmn20.xml&quot;)
      .deploy();
    
    // Start a process instance
    String procId = runtimeService.startProcessInstanceByKey(&quot;financialReport&quot;).getId();
    
    // Get the first task
    TaskService taskService = processEngine.getTaskService();
    List&lt;Task&gt; tasks = taskService.createTaskQuery().taskCandidateGroup(&quot;accountancy&quot;).list();
    for (Task task : tasks) {
      System.out.println(&quot;Following task is available for accountancy group: &quot; + task.getName());
      
      // claim it
      taskService.claim(task.getId(), &quot;fozzie&quot;);
    }
    
    // Verify Fozzie can now retrieve the task
    tasks = taskService.createTaskQuery().taskAssignee(&quot;fozzie&quot;).list();
    for (Task task : tasks) {
      System.out.println(&quot;Task for fozzie: &quot; + task.getName());
      
      // Complete the task
      taskService.complete(task.getId());
    }
    
    System.out.println(&quot;Number of tasks for fozzie: &quot; 
            + taskService.createTaskQuery().taskAssignee(&quot;fozzie&quot;).count());
    
    // Retrieve and claim the second task
    tasks = taskService.createTaskQuery().taskCandidateGroup(&quot;management&quot;).list();
    for (Task task : tasks) {
      System.out.println(&quot;Following task is available for accountancy group: &quot; + task.getName());
      taskService.claim(task.getId(), &quot;kermit&quot;);
    }
    
    // Completing the second task ends the process
    for (Task task : tasks) {
      taskService.complete(task.getId());
    }
    
    // verify that the process is actually finished
    HistoryService historyService = processEngine.getHistoryService();
    HistoricProcessInstance historicProcessInstance = 
      historyService.createHistoricProcessInstanceQuery().processInstanceId(procId).singleResult();
    System.out.println(&quot;Process instance end time: &quot; + historicProcessInstance.getEndTime());
  }

}</programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        This code is also available as a unit test shipped with the examples (yes, you should unit test your processes! 
        Read all about it in <link linkend="apiUnitTesting">the unit testing section</link>).
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="bpmnFirstExampleFutureEnhancements">
    
      <title>Future enhancements</title>
      
      <para>
        It's easy to see that this business process is too simple to be usable in reality.
        However, as you are going through the BPMN 2.0 constructs available in Activiti, 
        you will be able to enhance the business process by 
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              defining <emphasis role="bold">gateways</emphasis> that act as decisions.
              This way, a manager could reject the financial report which would recreate
              the task for the accountant. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              declaring and using <emphasis role="bold">variables</emphasis>,
              such that we can store or reference the report so that it can 
              be visualized in the form.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              defining a <emphasis role="bold">service task</emphasis> at the end of
              the process that will send the report to every shareholder.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              etc.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    
    </section>
  	
	</section>
</chapter>
