<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="activitiExplorer">

  <title>Activiti Explorer</title>
  
  <para>
    Activiti Explorer is a web application that is installed during the <link linkend="demo.setup">demo setup</link>.
    After logging into the application, you will see three large icons that show the main capabilities.
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.tabs.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Cases</emphasis>: case and task management functionality.
          Here you can see user tasks from running processes that are assigned to you, or
          see group tasks which you can claim. Note that in Explorer we talk about <emphasis>cases</emphasis>
          rather than <emphasis>tasks</emphasis>. As Explorer allows to relate content, divide
          work into subtasks, involve people in different roles, etc ... the term <emphasis>case</emphasis>
          covers better what is possible. Activiti Explorer as such can be used to create
          cases that are not related to processes (ie. standalone cases).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Process</emphasis>: shows the deployed process definitions,
          and allows to start new process instances.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Manage</emphasis>: only visible when the logged in user has 
          administrator rights. Allows to administrate the Activiti engine: manage users and groups,
          execute and see stuck jobs, see the database and deploy new process definitions.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist> 
  </para>
  
  <section>
  
    <title>Case overview</title>
    
    <para>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.case.overview.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
  <section>
  
    <title>Cases</title>
    
    <para>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.cases.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Inbox:</emphasis> shows the cases where the logged in user is the assignee.
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">My Cases:</emphasis> shows the cases where the logged in user is the owner.
            When you create a standalone case, you are automatically made owner of the case.
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Queued:</emphasis> shows the different groups which you are part
            of. Cases here must first be claimed before they can be completed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Involved:</emphasis> shows the cases where the logged in user is
            involved with (ie. not assignee or owner).
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Archived</emphasis> contains the past (historical) cases.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
  <section>
  
    <title>Start process instances</title>
    
    <para>
      The <emphasis role="bold">Process definitions</emphasis> tab, allows to see all process definitions
      that are deployed to the Activiti engine. You can start new process instances using the 
      button on the top right. If the process definition has a start <link linkend="forms">form</link>, the form will
      be displayed before starting the process instance.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.process.definitions.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
   <section>
  
    <title>My instances</title>
    
    <para>
      The <emphasis role="bold">My instances</emphasis> tab, shows all the process instances 
      where you currently have an uncompleted user task. It also visually shows the current activities
      of the process instance and the stored process variables.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.my.instances.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
    <section>
  
    <title>Administration</title>
    
    <para>
      The administration functionality is only available when the logged in user is part
      of the security group <emphasis>admin</emphasis>.
      When clicking the <emphasis>Manage</emphasis> icon, following tabs are available:
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Database:</emphasis> Shows the content of the database.
            Extremely useful when developing processes or troubleshooting problems.
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.database.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Deployments:</emphasis>
            Shows the current deployments of the engine, and see the content of a deployment (process definitions, images, business rules, etc.)
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.deployments.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
            You can also upload new deployments when clicking the <emphasis>deployment</emphasis> tab.
            Select a business archive or a bpmn20.xml file from your computer, or simply drag and drop to
            the designated area to deploy the new business processes.
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.upload.deployment.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Jobs:</emphasis> Shows the current jobs (timers, etc.) on the left
            and allows to manually execute them (eg. firing a timer before the deadline). Also
            shows any exceptions, if the jobs failed to execute (eg. mail server could not be reached)
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.jobs.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Users and Groups:</emphasis> manage the users and groups: create, edit and delete 
            users and groups. Relate users to groups such they have more privileges or they can see
            cases assigned to specific groups.
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.users.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
       
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
</chapter>
