<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="activitiExplorer">

  <title>Activiti Explorer</title>
  
  <para>
    Activiti Explorer is a web application that is included when you download Activiti from the
    Activiti website. The purpose of Explorer is not a finished, end-user ready application, but 
    rather to excersise and show the functionality of Activiti. As such, Explorer is meant as a demo,
    or maybe inspiration for people using Activti in there own applications. Out of the box, Explorer 
    uses an in-memory database, but it is easy to switch to your own database (see the applicationContext files in the WEB-INF folder).
  </para>
  <para> 
    After logging into the application, you will see three large icons that show the main capabilities.
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.tabs.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tasks</emphasis>: Task management functionality.
          Here you can see user tasks from running processes that are assigned to you, or
          see group tasks which you can claim. Explorer allows to relate content, divide
          work into subtasks, involve people in different roles, etc ... Explorer can also be used
          to create standalone tasks that are not related to any process.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Process</emphasis>: shows the deployed process definitions,
          and allows to start new process instances.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Manage</emphasis>: only visible when the logged in user has 
          administrator rights. Allows to administrate the Activiti engine: manage users and groups,
          execute and see stuck jobs, see the database and deploy new process definitions.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist> 
  </para>
  
  <section>
  
    <title>Process diagram</title>
    
    <para>
      The Explorer includes functionality to dynamically generate an overview of a process definition using the <ulink url="http://raphaeljs.com/">Raphaël</ulink> Javascript framework.
      This process image can only be generated when the process definition XML contains BPMN DI information. When there's no BPMN DI information in the process definition XML and the deployment contains a process definition image, that image will be shown.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.process.definition.image.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      When you don't want to use the Javascript process definition overview you can disable it in the ui.properties file
      <programlisting>
        activiti.ui.jsdiagram = false
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition to showing the process diagram in the Explorer it's also easy to include the process diagram anywhere you want.
      The following URL will show the process definition image, based on a process definition id: 
      <programlisting>
        http://localhost:8080/activiti-explorer/diagram-viewer/index.html?processDefinitionId=reviewSaledLead:1:36
      </programlisting>
      It's also possible to show the current state of a process instance by adding a processInstanceId request parameter like this: 
      <programlisting>
        http://localhost:8080/activiti-explorer/diagram-viewer/index.html?processDefinitionId=reviewSaledLead:1:36&amp;processInstanceId=41
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
  
    <title>Tasks</title>
    
    <para>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.cases.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Inbox:</emphasis> shows the tasks where the logged in user is the assignee.
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">My tasks:</emphasis> shows the tasks where the logged in user is the owner.
            When you create a standalone task, you are automatically made owner of the task.
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Queued:</emphasis> shows the different groups which you are part
            of. Tasks here must first be claimed before they can be completed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Involved:</emphasis> shows the tasks where the logged in user is
            involved with (i.e. not assignee or owner).
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Archived</emphasis> contains the past (historical) tasks.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
  <section>
  
    <title>Start process instances</title>
    
    <para>
      The <emphasis role="bold">Process definitions</emphasis> tab, allows to see all process definitions
      that are deployed to the Activiti engine. You can start new process instances using the 
      button on the top right. If the process definition has a start <link linkend="forms">form</link>, the form will
      be displayed before starting the process instance.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.process.definitions.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
   <section>
  
    <title>My instances</title>
    
    <para>
      The <emphasis role="bold">My instances</emphasis> tab, shows all the process instances 
      where you currently have an uncompleted user task. It also visually shows the current activities
      of the process instance and the stored process variables.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.my.instances.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
    <section>
  
    <title>Administration</title>
    
    <para>
      The administration functionality is only available when the logged in user is part
      of the security group <emphasis>admin</emphasis>.
      When clicking the <emphasis>Manage</emphasis> icon, following tabs are available:
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Database:</emphasis> Shows the content of the database.
            Extremely useful when developing processes or troubleshooting problems.
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.database.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Deployments:</emphasis>
            Shows the current deployments of the engine, and see the content of a deployment (process definitions, images, business rules, etc.)
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.deployments.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
            You can also upload new deployments when clicking the <emphasis>deployment</emphasis> tab.
            Select a business archive or a bpmn20.xml file from your computer, or simply drag and drop to
            the designated area to deploy the new business processes.
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.upload.deployment.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Jobs:</emphasis> Shows the current jobs (timers, etc.) on the left
            and allows to manually execute them (e.g. firing a timer before the deadline). Also
            shows any exceptions, if the jobs failed to execute (e.g. mail server could not be reached)
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.jobs.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Users and Groups:</emphasis> manage the users and groups: create, edit and delete 
            users and groups. Relate users to groups such they have more privileges or they can see
            tasks assigned to specific groups.
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explorer.users.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
       
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
  <section id="explorer.change.database">
    <title>Changing the database</title>  
    <para>
      To change the database that Explorer uses in the demo setup, change the properties file <literal>apps/apache-timcat-6.x/webapps/activiti-explorer/WEB-INF/classes/db.properties</literal>.
      Also, place a suitable database driver on the classpath (Tomcat shared libs or in <literal>apps/apache-timcat-6.x/webapps/activiti-explorer/WEB-INF/lib/</literal>).
    </para>
  </section>
  
</chapter>
