<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter>

  <title>Activiti Cycle</title>
  
  <para>
    Activiti Cycle is a web application that aims to provide a collaborative platform for business stakeholders, developers and IT operations people. It combines different repositories like the Activiti Modeler repository, Subversion or your local file system into a single view, which makes it easy to browse all the artifacts that are involved in the process of creating an executable business process. In addition to this, Activiti Cycle provides built in actions like moving artifacts between repositories or downloading different formats of process models, and a plug-in infrastructure for custom actions. Below is a screen shot of Cycle in the standard configuration as pre-configured in the demo setup.
  </para>
  
  <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.cycle.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
  
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>  
    <para>
      Since Activiti Cycle is meant to be used by people with entirely different roles, backgrounds and requirements, it was build with customization and extensibility in mind. However, the plug-in infrastructure which is already present in the current release is just a first step to make it possible to tailor Cycle to your specific needs. Future versions will provide a revised plug-in mechanism, a user interface to configure and plug in repositories, tags to dynamically add meta data to artifacts and a commenting function to directly collaborate on an artifact level. You can find a brief introduction to the initial version of Activiti Cycle and the vision behind it in the article <ulink url="http://www.bpm-guide.de/2010/08/27/activiti-cycle-explained/">Activiti Cycle explained</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Repositories</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.cycle.repositories.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    <para>
        The above image shows the Activiti Cycle repository tree.
        By default it provides access to the repository of the Activiti Modeler
        and a demo Eclipse workspace, which is located at
        <literal>${activiti.home}/workspace/activiti-cycle-examples</literal>
        in your local file system.
        The repositories are plugged in as repository connectors.
        You'll find the configuration as an XML string in
        the table <literal>CYCLE_CONFIG</literal> in the Activiti database,
        which you can access as described in <xref linkend="checking.database"/>.
        Here is the default configuration for the user kermit:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting>
      ...
      &lt;org.activiti.cycle.impl.conf.ConfigurationContainer&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;kermit&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;linkedConnectors&gt;
          &lt;org.activiti.cycle.impl.connector.signavio.SignavioConnectorConfiguration&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;Activiti Modeler&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;credentialsSaved&gt;false&lt;/credentialsSaved&gt;
            &lt;signavioBaseUrl&gt;http://localhost:8080/activiti-modeler/&lt;/signavioBaseUrl&gt;
            &lt;loginRequired&gt;false&lt;/loginRequired&gt;
          &lt;/org.activiti.cycle.impl.connector.signavio.SignavioConnectorConfiguration&gt;
          &lt;org.activiti.cycle.impl.connector.fs.FileSystemConnectorConfiguration&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;Eclipse Workspace (File System)&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;baseFilePath&gt;/path-to-activiti-home/activiti-5.0.beta2/workspace/activiti-cycle-examples&lt;/baseFilePath&gt;
          &lt;/org.activiti.cycle.impl.connector.fs.FileSystemConnectorConfiguration&gt;
        &lt;/linkedConnectors&gt; &lt;parentContainers/&gt;
      &lt;/org.activiti.cycle.impl.conf.ConfigurationContainer&gt;
      ...
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>
        Now, if you want to add, e.g., a Signavio Process Modeler repository,
        you can simply do this by adding a connector configuration to the XML configuration.
        If you need a Signavio account, you can register for a free trial
        at the <ulink url="http://www.signavio.com">Signavio web site</ulink>.
        Here is an example configuration:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting>
      ...
      &lt;org.activiti.cycle.impl.connector.signavio.SignavioConnectorConfiguration&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Signavio&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;credentialsSaved&gt;true&lt;/credentialsSaved&gt;
        &lt;user&gt;your user name&lt;/user&gt;
        &lt;password&gt;secret&lt;/password&gt;
        &lt;loginRequired&gt;true&lt;/loginRequired&gt;
        &lt;signavioBaseUrl&gt;https://editor.signavio.com/&lt;/signavioBaseUrl&gt;
      &lt;/org.activiti.cycle.impl.connector.signavio.SignavioConnectorConfiguration&gt;
      ...
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>
        Another thing you might consider
        is to add a collection of BPMN examples from
        the <ulink url="http://oryx-project.org/">Oryx Project</ulink>.
        In order to do this, all you need is the following connector configuration:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting>
      ...
      &lt;org.activiti.cycle.impl.connector.signavio.OryxConnectorConfiguration&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;oryx-project.org&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;credentialsSaved&gt;false&lt;/credentialsSaved&gt;
        &lt;signavioBaseUrl&gt;http://oryx-project.org/&lt;/signavioBaseUrl&gt;
        &lt;loginRequired&gt;false&lt;/loginRequired&gt;
      &lt;/org.activiti.cycle.impl.connector.signavio.OryxConnectorConfiguration&gt;
      ...
    </programlisting>
    	
    <para>
    	Activiti Cycle also has the capabilities to connect to SVN (Subversion) repositories. 
    	The following is an example configuration for the SVN Connector:    
    </para>
    
    <programlisting>
	...
	&lt;org.activiti.cycle.incubator.connector.svn.SvnConnectorConfiguration&gt;
		&lt;id&gt;RepositoryId (e.g. ProjectSVN)&lt;/id&gt;
		&lt;name&gt;Repository Name (My Project SVN)&lt;/name&gt;
		&lt;credentialsSaved&gt;true&lt;/credentialsSaved&gt;
		&lt;user&gt;user name&lt;/user&gt;
		&lt;password&gt;&lt;/password&gt;
		&lt;repositoryPath&gt;Path to your repository (e.g. http://mycompany.com/svn/projectName)&lt;/repositoryPath&gt;
		&lt;temporaryFileStore&gt;where the connector creates temporary files between commits (e.g. /tmp)&lt;/temporaryFileStore&gt;
	&lt;/org.activiti.cycle.incubator.connector.svn.SvnConnectorConfiguration&gt;
	...
	</programlisting>   
	<para> 
	Note: there are currently two configuration options for the Activiti Cycle SVN Connector:
	 <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>SVN is installed on the machine running Activiti and in the local PATH.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>You need to manually download the <ulink url="http://www.svnkit.org/">SVNKit</ulink> 
      library and install it. To this end, download the <literal>svnkit.jar</literal> and copy it to the following location: 
      <literal>${activiti.home}/apps/apache-tomcat-6.X.XX/lib/</literal>. (Tomcat restart required.) SVNKit cannot be bundled 
      with Activiti due to licensing restrictions.</para></listitem>
     </itemizedlist>	
     Please note that the SVN Connector is still in incubation and considered experimental.
    </para> 
	
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Artifacts and Actions</title>
    <para>
      When you click an item in the repository tree — in Activiti Cycle we refer to them as artifacts — the details are displayed on the right side. Currently, not all files are supported, but we aim to provide useful default views for the most common file types. In addition to the views, there is a set of actions that can be executed on the artifact. We currently distinguish between download links for different content representations, links that open external resources (e.g. the Signavio Modeler) and actions that require input properties.   
    </para>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.cycle.action.forms.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
  </section>
  
</chapter>
