<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter>

  <title>Activiti add-on components</title>
  
  <section id="cycle">
    <title>Cycle</title>
	  <para>
	    Started off as Activiti Cycle and now moved to the <ulink url="http://www.camunda.com/fox">camunda fox BPM Platform</ulink>, 
	    <ulink url="http://fox.camunda.com/doc/#cycle">Cycle</ulink> is web application that provides a collaborative platform for different stakeholders 
	    of BPM projects (Business, analysts, developers, managers, IT operations, ...).
	    It combines different data sources like the Activiti Modeler repository, Subversion or your local file system into a single view 
	    which makes it easy to browse all the artifacts (process models, development projects, requirements, ...)
	    that are involved in such a project. Additionally you can maintain relationships between them and Cycle
	    provides built in actions like moving artifacts between repositories or downloading different
	    formats of process models. A plug-in infrastructure is provided to hook in own repositories, actions or functionality.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    The concept of Cycle, especially with the philosophy of Business-IT-Alignment is new. You might best compare it 
	    to Application Lifecycle Management (ALM) tools. Cycle is developed by <ulink url="http://camunda.com">camunda</ulink>
	    and the documentation can be found in the <ulink url="http://fox.camunda.com/doc/#cycle">camunda fox documentation</ulink>.	    
	  </para>
  </section>

  <section id="activitiModeler">
    <title>Activiti Modeler based on Signavio Core components</title>
    <para>Signavio has a web based BPMN process modeler.  There is a tweaked version for 
    easy development with a file based backend.  That can be found in 
    the Google project <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/signavio-core-components/">Signavio core components</ulink>
    </para> 
    <para>We've documented some instructions on how to build it and how to use it with Activiti in the wiki page 
    <ulink url="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/ACT/How+to+build+Activiti+Modeler+from+Signavio">How to build Activiti Modeler from Signavio</ulink> 
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
