<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter>

  <title>Activiti Explorer</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>  
    <para>
      Activiti Explorer is a web application that provides access to the Activiti Engine runtime for all users of the system. It includes task management and process instance inspection.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tasks Management</title>
    <para>
      When you log in to Activiti Explorer, you will see the task page first. This page lists all tasks currently available and allows you to filter the view using any of the criteria in the left-hand panel. From here, all users can claim tasks and complete tasks.
    </para>
    <para>
      Task forms can be started directly from a URL, enabling links to forms to be embedded in places like emails, the URL is:
      <literal>http://localhost:8080/activiti-explorer/start?taskId=119</literal>, where <literal>119</literal> is the ID of the task with an associated form.
    </para>
     <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.explorer.tasks.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Process Instance Inspection</title>
    <para>
      The Processes tab enables users to view all deployed process definitions and provides the ability to start new process instances. Upon starting a process, any associated forms will automatically be displayed. As with the tasks, it is possible to directly start a process directly from a URL. That URL takes the form:
      <literal>http://localhost:8080/activiti-explorer/processes#start?id=financialReport:1</literal>, where <literal>financialReport:1</literal> is the ID of the process you want to start. The process will be started immediately and confirmation displayed on screen.
    </para>
    <para>
      The process list is paginated and can be sorted. The actions column can be extended to allow for other functions on a process instance (such as linking it to an Activiti Modeler install to enable users to view a process before starting it) by extending the processes WebScript.
     </para>
     <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/activiti.explorer.processes.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
  </section>
</chapter>
