<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter>
	<title>Advanced</title>
	
	<para>
	   The following sections cover advanced use cases of using Activiti, that go beyond typical execution of BPMN 2.0 processes.
	   As such, a certain proficiency and experience with Activiti is advisable to understand the material here. 
	</para>

	<section id="advanced_parseHandlers">
	
	   <title>Hooking into process parsing</title>
	
	   <para>
	       A bpmn 2.0 xml needs to be parsed to the Activiti internal model to be executed on the Activiti engine. This parsing
	       happens during a deployment of the process or when a process is not found in memory, and the
	       xml is fetched from the database. 
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	       For each of these processes, the <literal>BpmnParser</literal> class creates a new <literal>BpmnParse</literal> instance.
	       This instance will be used as container for all things that are done during parsing. The parsing on itself is very simple:
	       for each BPMN 2.0 element, there is a matching instance of the <literal>org.activiti.engine.parse.BpmnParseHandler</literal>
	       available in the engine. As such, the parser has a map which basically maps an BPMN 2.0 element class to an instance of 
	       <literal>BpmnParseHandler</literal>. By default, Activiti has <literal>BpmnParseHandler</literal> instances to handle
	       all supported elements and also uses it to attach execution listeners to steps of the process for creating the history.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	       It is possible to add custom instances of <literal>org.activiti.engine.parse.BpmnParseHandler</literal> to the Activiti engine.
	       An often seen use case is for example to add execution listeners to certain steps that fire events to some queue for event processing.
	       The history handling is done in such a way internally in Activiti.
	       To add such custom handlers, the Activiti configuration needs to be tweaked:
	       <programlisting>
&lt;property name=&quot;preBpmnParseHandlers&quot;&gt;
  &lt;list&gt;
    &lt;bean class=&quot;org.activiti.parsing.MyFirstBpmnParseHandler&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/list&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
	    
&lt;property name=&quot;postBpmnParseHandlers&quot;&gt;
  &lt;list&gt;
    &lt;bean class=&quot;org.activiti.parsing.MySecondBpmnParseHandler&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;bean class=&quot;org.activiti.parsing.MyThirdBpmnParseHandler&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/list&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;    
	       </programlisting>
	       The list of <literal>BpmnParseHandler</literal> instances that is configured in the <literal>preBpmnParseHandlers</literal> property
	       are added before any of the default handlers. Likewise, the <literal>postBpmnParseHandlers</literal> are added after those.
	       This can be important if the order of things matter for the logic contained in the custom parse handlers.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	       <literal>org.activiti.engine.parse.BpmnParseHandler</literal> is a simple interface:
	       <programlisting>
public interface BpmnParseHandler {
  
  Collection&lt;Class&gt;? extends BaseElement&gt;&gt; getHandledTypes();
  
  void parse(BpmnParse bpmnParse, BaseElement element);

}	       
	       </programlisting>
	       The <literal>getHandledTypes()</literal> method returns a collection of all the types handled by this parser. 
	       The possible types are a subclass of <literal>BaseElement</literal>, as directed by the generic type of the collection.
	       You can also extend the <literal>AbstractBpmnParseHandler</literal> class and override the <literal>getHandledType()</literal>
	       method, which only returns one Class and not a collection. This class contains also some helper methods
	       shared by many of the default parse handlers. 
	       The <literal>BpmnParseHandler</literal> instance will be called when the parser encounters any of the returned
	       types by this method. In the following example, whenever a process contained in a BPMN 2.0 xml is encountered, it 
	       will execute the logic in the <literal>executeParse</literal> method (which is a typecasted method that replaces
	       the regular <literal>parse</literal> method on the <literal>BpmnParseHandler</literal> interface). 
	       <programlisting>
public class TestBPMNParseHandler extends AbstractBpmnParseHandler&lt;Process&gt; {

  protected Class&lt;? extends BaseElement&gt; getHandledType() {
    return Process.class;
  }
  
  protected void executeParse(BpmnParse bpmnParse, Process element) {
     ..
  }

}	       
	       </programlisting>
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	       <emphasis role="bold">Important note:</emphasis> when writing custom parse handler, do not use any of the internal 
	       classes that are used to parse the BPMN 2.0 constructs. This will cause difficult to find bugs. The safe way to implement
	       a custom handler is to implement the <emphasis>BpmnParseHandler</emphasis> interface or extends the internal abstract class
	       <emphasis>org.activiti.engine.impl.bpmn.parser.handler.AbstractBpmnParseHandler</emphasis>.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
         It is possible (but less common) to replace the default <literal>BpmnParseHandler</literal> instances
         that are responsible for the parsing of the BPMN 2.0 elements to the internal Activiti model.
         This can be done by following snippet of logic:
         <programlisting>
&lt;property name=&quot;customDefaultBpmnParseHandlers&quot;&gt;
  &lt;list&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/list&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;         
         </programlisting>
         A simple example could for example be to force all of the service tasks to be asynchronous:
         <programlisting>
public class CustomUserTaskBpmnParseHandler extends ServiceTaskParseHandler {
  
  protected void executeParse(BpmnParse bpmnParse, ServiceTask serviceTask) {
    
    // Do the regular stuff
    super.executeParse(bpmnParse, serviceTask);
    
    // Make always async
    ActivityImpl activity = findActivity(bpmnParse, serviceTask.getId());
    activity.setAsync(true);
  }

}         
         </programlisting>          
	   </para>
        
	</section>
	
	<section id="advanced.uuid.generator">
	
	   <title>UUID id generator for high concurrency</title>
	   
	   <para>
	       In some (very) high concurrency load cases, the default id generator may cause exceptions due to not being able
	       to fetch new id blocks quickly enough. Every process engine has one id generator. The default id generator reserves
	       a block of id's in the database, such that no other engine will be able to use id's from the same block. During 
	       engine operations, when the default id generator notices that the id block is used up, a new transaction is started
	       to fetch a new block. In (very) limited use cases this can cause problems when there is a real high load. For 
	       most use cases the default id generator is more than sufficient. The default <literal>org.activiti.engine.impl.db.DbIdGenerator</literal>
	       also has a property <literal>idBlockSize</literal> which can be configured to set the size of the reserved block of id's
	       and to tweak the behavior of the id fetching. 
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	       The alternative to the default id generator is the <literal>org.activiti.engine.impl.persistence.StrongUuidGenerator</literal>,
	       which generates a unique <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universally_unique_identifier">UUID</ulink> locally and uses that
	       as identifier for all entities. Since the UUID is generated without the need for database access, it copes better with very high concurrency use cases.
	       Do note that performance may differ from the default id generator (both positive and negative) depending on the machine.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	       The UUID generator can be configured in the activiti configuration as follows:
<programlisting>
&lt;property name=&quot;idGenerator&quot;&gt;
    &lt;bean class=&quot;org.activiti.engine.impl.persistence.StrongUuidGenerator&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
</programlisting>	       
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	       The use of the UUID id generator depends on the following extra dependency:
	       <programlisting>
 &lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;com.fasterxml.uuid&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;java-uuid-generator&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;3.1.3&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</programlisting>
	   </para>
	
	</section>
	
	<section id="advanced.safe.bpmn.xml">
	
	   <title>Enable safe BPMN 2.0 xml</title>
	   
	   <para>
	     In most cases the BPMN 2.0 processes that are being deployed to the Activiti engine are under tight control
	     of eg. the development team. However, in some use cases it might be desirable to upload arbitrary BPMN 2.0 xml
	     to the engine. In that case, take into consideration that a user with bad intentions can bring the server 
	     down as described <ulink url="http://www.jorambarrez.be/blog/2013/02/19/uploading-a-funny-xml-can-bring-down-your-server/">here</ulink>.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	     To avoid the attacks described in the link above, a property <emphasis>enableSafeBpmnXml</emphasis> can be set on the process 
	     engine configuration:
	     <programlisting>&lt;property name=&quot;enableSafeBpmnXml&quot; value=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;</programlisting>
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	       <emphasis role="bold">By default this feature is disabled!</emphasis> The reason for this is that it relies on 
	       the availability of the <ulink url="http://download.java.net/jdk7/archive/b123/docs/api/javax/xml/transform/stax/StAXSource.html">StaxSource</ulink>
	       class. Unfortunately, on some platforms (eg. JDK 6, JBoss, etc.) this class is unavailable (due to older xml parser implementation)
	       and thus the safe BPMN 2.0 xml feature cannot be enabled. 
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>    
	       If the platform on which Activti runs does support it, do enable this feature. 
	   </para>
	
	</section>
	
</chapter>