<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../target/docbook-tool-1.0/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter>

  <title>Activiti KickStart</title>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>  
    <para>
      Activiti KickStart is a webbased tool to quickly create 'adhoc' business processes using
      a subset of constructs available to the Activiti engine.
      KickStart provides a simple UI that doesn't require to learn BPMN or any modeling environment, as 
      it works with concepts that are familiar to every business user. However, the processes that are 
      created using KickStart, are fully BPMN 2.0 compliant and can be used as a starting point
      for more complex BPM endeavours. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
      KickStart integrates perfectly with the Activiti engine. As such, processes created with KickStart
      are immediataly usable in Activiti Explorer and are visible in Probe.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      KickStart serves many business cases, but the following three are probably the most common:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Simple business processes: </emphasis> some processes are just simple
            by nature, and every company has them. Think about an expense process, a holiday leave process,
            a hiring process, etc... These kind of processes are probably already being done 
            using paper or e-mail. KickStart allows to model these processes quickly and change
            them whenever it is needed. As such, KickStart really lowers the threshold 
            to automate these business processes.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Prototyping: </emphasis> before diving into complex BPMN 2.0 modeling 
            and thinking about the corner cases of the process, it is often wise to get all people involved aligned and work out
            a prototype that shows the vision of what needs to be done. KickStart allows to do exatcly that:
            create a business process prototype on the fly, to get your ideas visible for everyone.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Adhoc work: </emphasis> in some cases, coordination is required
            between different people or groups in a company. You know how it normally goes: sending
            an email here, doing a telephone there ... which often ends up in a tarpit of nobody 
            knowing what or when something needs to be done. However, a business process management platform such as
            Activiti is an excellent way of distributing and follow-up everything, as it is
            intended to track exactly such things. KickStart allows you to create processes
            for adhoc work in a matter of minutes, and distribute and coordinate tasks between 
            people easily.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Following screenshots show the capabilities of Activiti KickStart. 
      Take for example the next picture. It shows how an expense process is created 
      in a matter of a few minutes.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.create.process.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      After clicking the save button, the process is immediately usable in Activiti Explorer:
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.process.in.explorer.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      KickStart also allows to define forms for every task:
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.form.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      Which are obviously directly usable in Activiti Explorer:
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.form.in.explorer.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      At any time during process creation, it is possible to view the corresponding BPMN 2.0 diagram
      of the business process:
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.diagram.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Whenever it is required, the processes defined with KickStart can be openend up and modified:
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.enhance.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Processes created with KickStart are fully compliant with the BPMN 2.0 XML, which means that
      the process can be imported into any BPMN 2.0 editor:
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.bpmn20.xml.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="kickstart.change.database">
    <title>Changing the database</title>  
    <para>
      Activiti KickStart is currently not yet using the REST API, but uses the service API by including the Activiti engine
      as a library. While Explorer, Probe and Cycle use the same mechanism for changing the database 
      (see <link linkend="changingTheDatabase">here</link>), the same does not yet apply for KickStart.
    </para>
    <para>
      To change the database that KickStart uses in the demo setup, generate a new activiti.cfg.jar, and place it
      in the <literal>apps/apache-tomcat-6.x/webapps/activiti-kickstart/WEB-INF/lib</literal> folder.
      Likewise, you must also place your database driver in the same folder. You can find
      the driver for your database (except Oracle) in <literal>setup/files/dependencies/libs/</literal>.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="kickstart.referencing.properties">
    <title>Referencing form properties</title>
    <para>
      The value that users fill in for the form properties can easily be used by referencing the 
      form property name. Take for example the following form:
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.form.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      This form has three form properties: <literal>Employee name, Amount and Motivation</literal>,
      which value can be used to populate the assignment, description and form title/description fields
      in following steps. For example, the <literal>Employee name</literal> property is used
      in the description of the following task:
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.reference.form.properties.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      Note that, in case the property has spaces, you can reference it by either keeping or 
      omitting the spaces.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="kickstart.capture.process.initiator">
    <title>Capture the process initiator</title>
    <para>
      Business processes get really useful when you can capture the initiator of a 
      process instance. Take for example the expense process that is shipped with the distribution.
      When somebody starts a process instance to reimburse his expenses, we want to know who 
      this was, so we can for example assign the first task to this person. 
    </para>
    <para>
      All processes generated with KickStart capture the initiator of the process in a property
      called <literal>initiator</literal>. Just <link linkend="kickstart.referencing.properties">reference the 'initiator' property</link>,
      as shown in the following picture. In this example, the 'Request expense refund' task
      will be assigned to whoever started the process instance.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/kickstart.capture.initiator.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>

